A Finding Aid to the Esther McCoy Papers, circa 1876-1990, bulk 1938-1989, in the Archives of American Art AAA.mccoesth
Archives of American Art
- Photographs and Slides, circa 1876-1989; Series 9; (Boxes 31-38, 41-46, 51; 8.7 linear feet)
  - Case Study Houses, circa 1945-1962; 9.3
    - Soriano, Raphael, Case Study House 1950, circa 1950; (Photographs by Marvin Rand have not been scanned) (Box 37, Folder 17-18)
    - Spaulding, Sumner, and John Rex, Case Study House #2, circa 1945-1947 (Box 37, Folder 19)
    - Walker, Rodney, Case Study Houses #16, #17, #18, circa 1946-1948; (Photographs by Julius Shulman have not been scanned) (Box 37, Folder 20)
    - Wurster, William W. and Theodore Bernardi, Case Study House #3, circa 1949; (Photographs by Julius Shulman have not been scanned) (Box 37, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Photographs, circa 1952-1969; 9.4
    This subseries consists of exhibition photographs, the bulk of which document the 1967 exhibition "Ten Italian Architects" at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art. Photograph documentation of this exhibition includes installation views and photographs used for the exhibition catalog. Other photographs related to this exhibition are arranged by name of architect. Not all of the photographs found here were used in the catalog. Researchers should note that additional documentation of this exhibition catalog, written by McCoy, can be found among her architectural writings in Series 4.2: Exhibition Catalogs. Additional files in this subseries include installation views of an exhibition of work by Antoni Gaudi and copies of photographs used in three other exhibitions.
    The bulk of this subseries has been scanned.
    - Art Institute of Chicago, "Louis Sullivan and the Architecture of Free Enterprise,", 1956 (Box 37, Folder 22)
    - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, "Ten Italian Architects" (Box 37)
      - Installation Views, 1967 (Box 37, Folder 23)
      - Photographs for Exhibition Catalog, 1967 (Box 37, Folder 24)
      - Architect, Franco Albini and Franca Helg, circa 1960s (Box 37, Folder 25-26)
      - Architect, B. B. P. R. (Belgiojoso, Peressutti, and Rogers) (2 folders), circa 1952-1969 (Box 37, Folder 27-28)
      - Architect, Giancarlo de Carlo, circa 1950s, 1964 (Box 37, Folder 29)
      - Architect, Ignazio Gardella, circa 1954-1958 (Box 37, Folder 30)
      - Architect, Angelo Mangiarotti, circa 1961-1963 (Box 37, Folder 31-32)
      - Architect, Giovanni Michelucci, circa 1963-1967 (Box 37, Folder 33)
      - Architect, Alberto Rosselli, circa 1960s (Box 37, Folder 34)
      - Architect, Gino Valle, circa 1963 (Box 37, Folder 35)
      - Architect, Vittoriano Vigano, circa 1960s (Box 37, Folder 36)
      - Miscellaneous Photographs, circa 1960s (Box 37, Folder 37)
      - Photograph Negatives, circa 1960s (Box 37, Folder 38)
      - Photograph Transparencies, circa 1960s (Box 37, Folder 39)
    - Museum of Modern Art, "Architecture of Antoni Gaudi,", 1958 (Box 37, Folder 40)
    - Museum of Modern Art, "Stairs,", 1963 (Box 37, Folder 41)
    - Museum of Modern Art, "Architecture Without Architects,", 1964-1965 (Box 37, Folder 42)
  - Research Photographs, circa 1915-1970s; 9.5
    Found here are photographs which were primarily compiled by McCoy as research photographs during her work as a writer. Many of these photographs were taken to accompany her series of travel articles written for the Los Angeles Times. Files are arranged by subject, and often document craft and architecture in various countries such as Italy, Mexico, Brazil, and Israel. Also found are files of photographs documenting California architectural history. Researchers should note that related photographs may be found among McCoy's architectural writings in Series 4.
    Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Art Deco in Los Angeles, circa 1930s-1960s; (Photographs by Julius Shulman have not been scanned) (Box 37, Folder 43)
    - Brazil, circa 1959; (Oversized items housed in Box 43) (Box 37, Folder 44)
    - Brussels World's Fair, 1958 (Box 37, Folder 45)
    - California Architectural History, circa 1920s-1970s; (Photographs by Julius Shulman have not been scanned) (Box 37, Folder 46-47)
    - Colorado, circa 1965 (Box 37, Folder 48)
    - France, circa 1960s (Box 37, Folder 49)
    - Ghana, 1965 (Box 37, Folder 50)
    - Guatemala, circa 1960s (Box 37, Folder 51)
    - Israel, circa 1960 (Box 37, Folder 52)
    - Italy (Box 37)
      - Architecture and Design, 1956-circa 1960s (Box 37, Folder 53)
      - Basketry, circa 1950s (Box 37, Folder 54)
      - Ceramics, circa 1952-1960 (Box 37, Folder 55-57)
      - Furniture, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 37, Folder 58-60)
      - Glass, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 38, Folder 1-2)
      - Handbags, circa 1950s (Box 38, Folder 3)
      - Ivrea (Olivetti Company), circa 1960s (Box 38, Folder 4)
      - Marble, circa 1954-1964 (Box 38, Folder 5-6)
      - People and Landscapes, circa 1959-1960 (Box 38, Folder 7-10)
      - Piedmont Castles, circa 1960s (Box 38, Folder 11)
      - Sculpture, circa 1950s (Box 38, Folder 12)
      - Textiles, circa 1950s (Box 38, Folder 13)
      - Wood Crafts, circa 1950s (Box 38, Folder 14)
    - Mexico (Box 38)
      - Cuernavaca, circa 1954 (Box 38, Folder 15)
      - Folk Architecture, circa 1950s (Box 38, Folder 16-18)
      - Furniture and Crafts, circa 1950s (Box 38, Folder 19-20)
      - University of Mexico, Campus, circa 1950s; (Oversized items housed in Box 43) (Box 38, Folder 21)
      - University of Mexico, Estadio Olimpico, circa 1952; (Oversized items housed in Box 43) (Box 38, Folder 22)
      - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s (Box 38, Folder 23-28)
      - Negatives, circa 1950s (Box 38, Folder 29)
    - Norwegian Crafts, circa 1960s (Box 38, Folder 30)
    - San Diego Architecture, circa 1915-1970s; (Oversized items housed in Box 43) (Box 38, Folder 31)
    - Shrines of Nigeria, 1967 (Box 38, Folder 32)
    - Triennale of Milan 1957, circa 1957 (Box 38, Folder 33-35)
    - Unidentified Architecture, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 38, Folder 36-37)
    - Oversized Photographs of Brazil, circa 1959; (See also Box 37, Folder 44) (Box 43)
    - Oversized Photographs of University of Mexico, Campus, circa 1950s; (See also Box 38, Folder 21) (Box 43)
    - Oversized Photographs of University of Mexico, Estadio Olimpico, circa 1952; (Scanned with Box 38, Folder 22) (Box 43)
    - Oversized Photographs of San Diego Architecture, circa 1915-1970s; (Scanned with Box 38, Folder 31) (Box 43)
  - Slides, circa 1950s-1980s; 9.6
    Found her are approximately 3,600 slides of examples of architects' works collected by Esther McCoy over the course of her career. Most slides included a handwritten label.
    This subseries has not been scanned.
    Slides are arranged either by architect's name or geographic location (U.S. state or country).
    - Architects: A, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 44, Folder 1)
      Abell, Thornton
      Ain, Gregory
    - Architects: A-D, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 44, Folder 2)
      Albini, Franco
      Artigas, Francisco
      Barragan, Luis
      BBPR
      Buff, Straub, and Hensman
      Byers, John
      Cacho, J. Francisco Serrano
      Callister, C. W.
      Candela, Felix
      Cheval, Ferdinand
      Clements, Stiles O.
      Coate, Roland E.
      Le Corbusier
      Davidson, J. R.
    - Architects: D-E, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 44, Folder 3)
      Del Moral, Enrique
      DeMars, Esherick, and Olsen
      DMJM
      Dorman, Richard
      Eames, Charles
    - Architects: E-G, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 44, Folder 4)
      Ehrlich, Steven
      Ellwood, Craig
      Fenyes, Eva Scott
      Frey, Albert
      Furness, Frank
      Gardella, Iganzio
      Gaudi, Antoni
      Gebhard, David
      Gehry, Frank
      Gill, Irving
    - Architects: G-H, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 44, Folder 5)
      Greene and Greene
      Gropius, Walter
      Harris, George
      Harris, Harwell
    - Architects: H-M, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 44, Folder 6)
      Hollein, Hans
      Honnold and Rex
      Horta, Victor
      Jenney, William L.
      Jones, A. Quincy
      Kahn, Louis
      Kappe, Ray
      Killingsworth, Brady, and Smith
      Koenig, Pierre
      Kump, Ernest J.
      Loos, Adolf
      Lumsden, Anthony
      Mackintosh, Charles R.
    - Architects: M, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 45, Folder 1)
      Maillart
      Mangiarotti, Angelo
      Maston, Carl
      May, Cliff
      Maybeck, Bernard
      McKim, Mead and White
      Mendelsohn, Eric
      Michelucci, Giovanni
      Mies van der Rohe, Ludwig
      Miller, Leroy
      Moore, Charles
    - Architects: M-P, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 45, Folder 2)
      Morgan, Julia
      Morphosis
      Mosher and Drew
      Myers, Barton
      Nervi, Pier L.
      Neutra, Richard
      O'Gorman, Juan
      Olbrich, Joseph
      Palladio, Andrea
      Pani, Mario
      Pei, I. M.
      Pelli, Cesar
    - Architects: P-R, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 45, Folder 3)
      Piano and Rogers
      Ponti, Gio
      Rapson, Ralph
      Requa, Richard
      Rice, Lillian
      Richardson, Henry Hobson
    - Architects: R-S, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 45, Folder 4)
      Riggs, Lutah
      Roche, Kevin
      Rosselli, Alberto
      Sant'Elia, Antonio
      Scarpa, Carlo
      Schindler, R. M.
    - Architects: Schindler, R. M., circa 1950s-1980s (Box 45, Folder 5)
    - Architects: S, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 45, Folder 6)
      Skidmore, Owings, and Merrill
      Schulitz, Helmut C.
      Smith, G. W.
      Smith, Jones and Contini
      Smith, Neill
      Smith and Williams
      Smithson, Peter
      Soleri, Paolo
      Soriano, Raphael
    - Architects: S-W, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 46, Folder 1)
      Spaulding and Rex
      Sterling, James
      Stern, Peter
      Stickney and Hull
      Stone, Edward D.
      Terragni, Giuseppe
      Trubeck and Wislocki
      Valle, Gino
      Venturi and Rauch
      Vigano, Vittoriano
      Voysey, Charles
      Wagner, Otto
      Walker, Rodney
      Webb, Philip
      Weston, Eugene
      Wright, Frank Lloyd
    - Architects: W, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 46, Folder 2)
      Wright, Lloyd
      Wurster, William
    - Location, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 46, Folder 3)
      Arizona
      California
    - Location, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 46, Folder 4)
      Colorado
      Connecticut
      Hawaii
      Illinois
      New York
      Ohio
      Virginia
      Austria
      England
    - Location, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 46, Folder 5)
      France
      Italy
      Japan
    - Location, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 46, Folder 6)
      Mexico
    - Location, Mexico, 1969, 1978 (Box 38, Folder 38)
    - Location, Netherlands, 1970 (Box 38, Folder 39)
    - Location, Scotland, 1970 (Box 38, Folder 40)
    - Personal Photographs, 1950-1979 (Box 38, Folder 41)
    - Unidentified Slides, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 38, Folder 42)
- Audio and Video Recordings, 1930-1984; Series 10; (Boxes 38-40, 47, 52; 2.5 linear feet)
  Found here are interview recordings, commercially produced music recordings, and a videocassette of Esther McCoy's 80th birthday party. Interview recordings include taped, untranscribed interviews with architects, people associated with architectural projects, and artists. Recordings were made either on sound tape reels (3 in., 1/4 in. tape) or sound cassettes. All interviews were conducted by Esther McCoy, unless otherwise noted, as part of her research for magazine articles and books, including many interviews from 1964 and 1965 which were used for her article, "Young Architects: The Small Office," published in Arts & Architecture magazine (February/March 1966).
  All of the sound tape reels have been digitized by the Archives of American Art for reference use. Some duplicate cassettes have also been created for reference use. All items listed are original recordings unless otherwise indicated in the item heading.
  Interview recordings are arranged in rough alphabetical order by interviewee. Where different subjects were taped on the same reel, they are listed together in order to reflect the physical arrangement of the interviews on the reels.
  - Interview Recordings (Box 38)
    - Gregory Ain, interviewed by Kathryn Smith, 1977; (1 sound cassette and 2 duplicate sound cassettes) (Box 38, Item 1)
    - Christopher Alexander, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 1)
    - Donlyn Lyndon, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 2)
    - Francisco Artigas, 1970; (4 sound cassettes and 3 duplicate sound cassettes) (Box 39, Item 3)
    - Francisco Artigas, 1971; (4 sound cassettes and 4 duplicate sound cassettes) (Box 39, Item 4)
    - Gunnar Birkerts, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 5)
    - Ray Bradbury, 1972; (1 sound cassette) (Box 39, Item 6)
    - Charles Brewer, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 7)
    - Kevin Roche, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 8)
    - Mario Ciampi, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 9)
    - David Crane, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 10)
    - Peter Chermayeff and Paul Dietrich, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 11)
    - J. R. Davidson, 1974; (2 sound tape reels) (Box 39, Item 12)
    - Robert Geddes, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 13)
    - Virgil and Minna Geddes, circa 1965; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 14)
    - Gerhard Kallman and Noel McKinnell, circa 1965; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 15)
    - Paul Dietrich, 1965; (3 sides of 2 sound tape reels) (Box 39, Item 16)
    - Peter Chermayeff, 1965; (2 sides of 2 sound tape reels) (Box 39, Item 17)
    - John Harkness, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 18)
    - Iqbal Geoffrey, 1965; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 19)
    - Dorothy Grotz, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 20)
    - Konrad Wachsmann, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 21)
    - Harwell Hamilton Harris, 1980; (3 sound tape reels and 3 duplicate sound cassettes) (Box 39, Item 22)
    - Bernard Huet, circa 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 23)
    - A. Quincy Jones, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 24)
    - Robert Jones, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 25)
    - Robert and Dorothy Kahan, 1980; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 39, Item 26)
    - Louis Kahn, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 1)
    - Keith Kalb, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 2)
    - Max and Rita Lawrence, 1977; (2 sound tape reels) (Box 40, Item 3)
    - Leah Lovell, undated; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 4)
    - Philip Lovell, interviewed by Kathryn Smith and Esther McCoy, 1977; (1 sound cassette and 1 duplicate sound cassette) (Box 40, Item 5)
    - Cliff May, interviewed by Evelyn Hitchcock, 1983; (1 sound cassette) (Box 40, Item 6)
    - Peter Millard, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 7)
    - Charles Brewer, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 8)
    - Richard Neutra, 1960s; (1 sound tape reel and 2 duplicate sound cassettes) (Box 40, Item 9)
      (Interview conducted and tape produced by Bethlehem Steel)
    - Cesar Pelli, 1969; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 10)
    - Cesar Pelli, undated; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 11)
    - James Polshek, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 12)
    - Martin Price, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 13)
    - Jonas Salk, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 14)
    - Louis Sauer, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 15)
    - Aaron Schreier, undated; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 15)
    - Ben Southland, 1969; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 17)
    - Edgardo Contini, 1969; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 18)
    - Stickney & Hull, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 19)
    - Paul Thiry, 1965; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 20)
    - Karl Van Leuven and Herman Guttman of Victor Gruen Associates, 1969; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 21)
    - Robert Venturi, 1964; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 22)
    - Tim Vreeland, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 23)
    - Tim Vreeland and Ramaldo Giurgola, 1964; (2 sides of 2 sound tape reels) (Box 40, Item 24)
    - Ramaldo Giurgola, 1964; (1 side of 1 sound tape reel) (Box 40, Item 25)
    - Evans Woollen, undated; (2 sound tape reels) (Box 40, Item 26)
    - Lloyd Wright, 1970; (2 sound cassettes and 1 duplicate sound cassette) (Box 40, Item 27)
    - Lloyd Wright, undated; (2 sound tape reels) (Box 40, Item 28)
  - "Anthem of the U.S.S.R.,", circa 1945; (1 sound disc) (Box 47, Item 1)
  - "Free and Equal Blues,", circa 1945; (1 sound disc) (Box 47, Item 2)
  - "Preludio A Cristobal Colon,", 1930; (1 sound disc) (Box 47, Item 3)
  - "Songs of the Red Army,", 1940; (Album, 3 sound discs) (Box 47, Item 4)
  - Esther McCoy's 80th Birthday Party, Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles, 1984; (1 videocassette and 2 duplicate videocassettes) (Box 52, Item 1)